Hello everyone, I am Kaichao
大家好我是凯超
Today's lesson will explain rust enum
我们今天的课程会讲解rust枚举
data type and pattern matching
数据类型和模式匹配
Today's course includes
今天课程内容包括
a brief introduction to enumerated data types
枚举数据类型的简单介绍
includes commonly used enums
包括常用的枚举数据类型
such as Option and Result
如 Option 和 Result
and how to use pattern matching.
以及如何使用模式匹配
enum is one of the most commonly used data types in Rust
枚举
是 Rust 中最常用的数据类型之一
it can be used to represent multiple variants
它可以用来表示多个变体
that is to say
也就是说
multiple possibilities for value of the same type.
同一类型的值有多种可能性
Like our traffic lights,
比如说我们的交通信号灯
it can be red, green or yellow.
它可以是红色、绿色或者黄色
But it shouldn't display multiple colors at the same time.
但是它不能同时显示多种颜色
Another example is the ip address we use
另外一个例子是我们使用的ip地址
In a logic we may deal with the IPv4 protocol
在一段逻辑里面我们可能
处理的是IPv4协议
or the IPv6 protocol
也可能是IPv6协议
But we can't handle multiple protocols
但是我们不可能在这段逻辑里面
at the same time.
同时处理多个协议
enum is defined via
枚举的定义是通过
a keyword enum
enum这样的一个关键词来
实现的
Here we define an enum
这里我们定义了一个枚举
called TrafficLight
叫做 TrafficLight
交通信号灯
it has three variants
它有三个变体
The first one is the red light
第一个是红灯red
the second is green and the third is yellow
第二个是green 第三个是yellow
We add two colons like this
我们通过两个冒号这样的方式来
to use a variant
使用这样的一个变体
and assign it to our variable yellow
并将它赋值给我们的变量yellow
Similarly, we have another enum example
类似的我们定义了另外一个枚举叫做
IpAddr, ip address
IpAddr ip地址
It has two variants one is V4 and the other is V6
它有两个变体一个是V4, 一个是V6
Variants of enum
枚举的变体
can include any type of data
它内部可以包含任意类型的数据
for example, we use string here
比如这里的字符串
can also be numbers, structs,
或者数值、结构体
other enums etc.
以及其他的枚举等等
Here we also use two colons
这里我们同样的用两个冒号
to construct an ip address IPv4
构造了一个
IPv4这样的一个ip地址
Its content is
那它里面的内容是
a string 127.0.0.1
127.0.0.1 这样的字符串
and assign it to our variable home
把它赋值给
我们的变量 home
In addition to the fact that the variant can contain data
那除了变体里面可以包含数据之外
we can also define methods for enum
我们可以对枚举定义方法
and implement trait which is similar to interface
实现 trait 也就是接口
We haven't talked about the concept of traits
我们还没有讲过接口的具体概念
We will skip it here, and talk about traits later.
那这里我们就先跳过
Now let's see how to define a method for enum.
现在我们来看一下怎样为
枚举定义方法
Here I am using the playground from Rust
这里我使用的是 Rust 语言的 playground
it is a simple, small online environment
也就是一个简便的
用来测试开发的一个线上小环境
for testing and development
The url is play.rust-lang.org
它的路径是play.rust-lang.org
So here we have a main function
那这里我们有一个main函数
is the execution entry point of our program
是我们程序的执行入口
We define an enum of traffic lights
我们定义一个交通信号灯这样的枚举
it has three variants that we have just seen
它有三个变体我们刚才已经看到过了
Next
接着呢
For TrafficLight
我们为我们的交通信号灯
enum
这样的一个枚举
we will implement a method called "time"
实现一个方法是time
it returns an integer
它可以返回一个整数
we set the return value to 60 here
那我们这里返回固定的值是60
Certainly
当然
We can also return a different value
我们也可以根据我们交通信号灯
base on different variants of TrafficLight
不同的变体
返回不同的数值
This requires using pattern match
这就需要用到我们的pattern match
也就是模式匹配
we will introduce it later
我们接下来再去介绍
We create a variable in the main function
我们在main函数里面构造这样的一个变量
its value is red traffic light
是我们的红色交通信号灯
we want to print the duration of a red traffic light
打印我们
红色交通信号灯所持续的时间
let's call the time function
调用我们的time方法
execute it
执行
Here you can see
可以看到当
when a variant is not used
定义的变体没有用到的时候
it will report a warning
它会报一个warning
Here we can see the result
那这里我们可以看到输出的结果
it has returned 60
已经返回了60
Next, let's look at one of the most commonly used enum
接着我们来看一个最常用的枚举之一
Option
It is used to represent two possible scenarios
它是用来表示两种可能的场景
One scenario is that some value (in specific type) exist
一种是存在某种类型的值
The other is that no such value
另外一种是不存在有效的该类型的值
It is commonly used for exception handling
它是用于异常处理的一种常见机制
The official definition uses a generic T
官方
的定义的话其实是通过一个泛型T
to accept different data types
来接受不同的数据类型
Here we haven't introduce generics yet
那这里我们因为没有介绍泛型
So we don't pay much attention to the official definition
所以我们不去关注官方这个定义
I will use an integer type, u8
我们以一个简单的
as an example to make a introduction
整数u8类型为例来进行介绍
We define an enum
我们定义了一个枚举
its name is MyOption
它的名字是 MyOption
it has two variants
那它有两个变体
One is Some(u8)
一个是 Some(u8)
That is, when there is value
也就是当有值的时候
Its type is u8
它的值是一个u8
Another variant is None
另外一个变体是None
That is, there is no valid integer value
也就是不存在一个有效的整数值
The option enum defines a series of
option枚举里面定义了一系列
easy-to-use methods
好用的方便的方法
For example is_some
比如 is_some
to check if there is value
来检查我们当前的这个option
in the current optional variable
变量是不是有值
Another method is map
另外一个方法是 map
it will operates on the value in the option
会对我们的 option 里面的值进行操作
If it is None, do nothing
如果是None的话 就什么都不做
returns None
还是返回一个None
If it is a Some
那如果是一个Some
then it will operate on the value inside
的话就会对里面的值进行操作
Then
然后将
returns the result of the operation
操作的结果返回
map_or is similar to map
map_or 和 map 类似
It will also operate on the value in it
里面如果有值的话进行操作
If there is no value, return a default value instead
如果没值的话就返回一个默认值
unwrap will open our option
unwrap会打开我们的option
when the value is None and unwrap it
当unwrap的是None的话
the program will exit with an exception
会使程序异常退出
There are many other methods defined in option
option里面定义的方法其实还有很多
You can refer to the documentation of Rust
大家可以参考Rust的应用文档
We have given the link here
我们这里已经给出了链接
Another commonly used enum is Result
另外一个常用的枚举是Result
It is also an exception handling mechanism
它也是一种异常处理的机制
There are two scenarios
表示的场景有两种
In one scenario, it represents a correct value in a specific type
一种是正确的某种类型的值
The other is
另外一种是
another type of value representing the error message
表示错误信息的另一类型的值
The official definition is through two generics
那官方定义是通过两个泛型
T and E, E represents the error message, T represents the correct value
T 和 E, E表示错误信息, T表示正确的值
Let's make our generics concrete here
那我们这里把我们的泛型具体化
Take our integer u8 and error message is string as an example
以我们的整数 u8 和错误信息 string 为例
Then we can define such an enum
那我们定义了这样一个枚举
its name is MyResult
它的名字是 MyResult
It has two variants one is Ok
它有两个变体一个是 Ok
the value inside is an integer u8
然后里面的值是一个整数 u8
Another variant is Error
另外变体是 Error
it represents error message
它表示错误信息
it has a value in it, which is a string
它里面有值是一个字母串 string
The methods defined by result, like is_ok
result定义的方法有is_ok
to check that
来检查我们的
the Result is a variant of Ok or not
Result是不是一个Ok这样的一个变体
and map
以及map
It will operate on the value and returns it
Result里面是Ok的话
if the variant of our Result is Ok
会对值进行操作并返回
If it is an Error variant, do nothing
如果是error错误的话不做任何操作
map_or is similar to map
map_or和map类似
if it is error
那如果是error的话
it returns a default value.
返回一个默认值
Unwrap will try to get the value in Result enum
unwrap会打开我们的Result类型
If it is an Error
如果是一个error的话会
our program will exit with an exception
使我们的程序异常并退出
There are many methods in Result enum
Result类型提供的方法还有很多
Its documentation is here
它的文档在这里
Pattern match
pattern match也就是模式匹配
it is a very useful feature
它是现代编程语言一个非常
强大的功能特性
almost all modern programming languages
那基本上所有的现代
编程语言都具备这样的一个
have such a feature
特性
It can easily implement conditional branch management
他可以方便的实现条件分支管理
You can imagine that it is an enhanced version of if else
你可以想象成他是一个if else的加强版
Pattern match
模式匹配
works with almost all data types
几乎适用于所有的数据类型
including basic types such as u8
包括基本类型比如说整数u8
bool, string
布尔, 字符串
complex types such as structs
复杂类型比如结构体
enums and tuples
枚举和元组tuple
When using pattern match
在使用模式匹配时
the matching must be exhaustive
他要求我们的匹配必须彻底、完备
if there are situations that are not included
也就是说如果有分支没有覆盖到
compilation error will raise
会发生编译错误
For example
比如
if we only match Some variant on Option enum
option如果只匹配了some
but not match for None, an error will be reported
而没有匹配none的话就会报错误
Underline
下划线
is usually put at the end and represents default behaviour
通常放到最后用来作为默认的
or a process that the code doesn't care about
或者说是代码所不关心的一个
流程分支
Use it with caution
要谨慎使用
otherwise there will be bugs
不然的话会产生bug
When you use the underscore
也就是说当你使用了下划线
but ignore some scenarios that need to be dealt with
但是又忽略了某种
需要处理的场景的时候
your code will not work as expected
你的代码就会
不是按期望的那样所运行
Here we give two examples of pattern matching
这里我们举两个模式匹配的例子
We defined a variable called value
我们定义了一个变量叫做value
it is an integer u8
它是一个整数u8
The value is 0, then we match this value
值是0 那我们对这个值进行匹配
If it is 1 or 3
如果是1或者3的时候
We will print a corresponding string
我们就打印对应的一个字符串
If other values
那如果是其他数值
we just do nothing
我们就什么操作都不做
Another example is
另外一个例子是
We pattern match the option
我们对option进行模式匹配
Here we define a function called plus_one
这里我们定义了一个函数叫做plus_one
It receives a parameter, an option i32
它接收一个参数是一个option i32
returns an option i32
返回一个option i32
Then here we put our
这里对我们的
parameter for pattern matching
参数进行模式匹配
If it is None, return it
如果是None的话返回None
if Some
如果是 Some
Then we add 1 to the value
那我们对里面的值进行加1
then return
然后返回
You see that
可以看到我们
the value is Some(5)
变量如果是Some(5)
Then we call our plus_one function
那我们调用我们的plus_one函数
the input is Some(5)
传入的Some(5)
then it will return Some(6)
那我们就会返回一个Some(6)
When the input is None
当我们传入的是None的时候
our plus_one function returns None
我们的plus_one函数返回的还是一个None
Here we use map
这里我们来用map
to rewrite the plus_one function
对plus_one函数进行改造
We first define a variable
我们首先定义一个变量
it is an option
它是一个option的值
with a value, Some(5)
它是有值的Some(5)
Then we use map
那我们再用它的map
to add 1 to the value
对里面的值进行加1
The map receives a closure
map接收的是一个closure
that is, a function call
也就是一个函数调用
Then we print the output
然后我们打印对应的输出
Next, let's test the scenario that the value is None
接着我们来测一下如果值是None
的情况下
we first define a variable, its value is None
我们首先定义值为None的变量
Here we need to define the type
这里我们要显示的给出类型定义
because the compiler can't infer it from None
因为编译器通过None推断不出来变量的类型
If it is Some, the type of the value inside can be inferred
如果是Some的时候可以推断出里面的值的类型
then we call the map function
那我们同样的调用我们的map函数
give it a closure
给一个closure
then print the result
然后打印对应的结果
Let's try
我们可以看一下对应的结果
You can see that it is None
可以看到它是None
A special syntax in pattern matche is
模式匹配的一个
if let
比较独特的语法是if let
It is used when we only care about
它适用的场景是当我们只关心
one branch
一个分支时
For example
比如这里我们
we define a variable called some_u8_value
定义了一个变量是some_u8_value
its value is Some(3)
那它的值是一个Some(3)
we can match this value
我们可以对这个值进行匹配
Print when it's Some(3)
当它是
Some(3)的时候打印
in other cases
如果是其他情况的时候
we do nothing
我们就不做操作
We can rewrite it with if let
我们可以把这样的一个语法
通过if let进行重写
It's separated by the equal sign
我们用等号分隔
the left is the pattern we need to match
等号左边是我们需要匹配的模式
Some(3)
The right side, it's the value we need to match
那等号右边的话是我们需要匹配的值
which is some_u8_value
就是我们的some_u8_value
When the match is successful, we do the corresponding operation
当匹配成功的时候我们做对应的操作
that is, print
也就是打印
do nothing when the match is unsuccessful
当匹配不成功的时候什么都不做
Using if let will lose the sanity check
使用if let会失去完备性检查
So be careful when using it
所以使用的时候要格外小心
That's all for today's lesson, thank you all
今天的课程内容就到这里谢谢大家